

GRADUATE RESEARCH ASSISTANT · COMPUTATIONAL SCIENTIST

4613, Oxgang Dr, Pflugerville, Austin, TX-78660

□ (+1) 925-336-5931 | Shreyas.gaikwad@utexas.edu | 🌴 shreyas911.github.io | 🖸 Shreyas911 | 🛅 shreyasg911

Summary_

I am a third year Ph.D. student at the Oden Institute for Computational Engineering and Sciences at The University of Texas at Austin. I am broadly interested in machine learning, optimization, inverse problems, uncertainty quantification, computational glaciology, and computational oceanography. I am currently working on two major projects - 1. Paleochronometry as a control problem for recovering Holocene climate variations over the Greenland Ice Sheet, 2. Designing a Deep Learning Emulator for the dynamics of sea ice within the general ocean circulation model, MITgcm. Over the course of my work, I have collaborated with researchers from MIT, Argonne National Laboratory, UC San Diego, Hokkaido University, French Institute for Research in Computer Science and Automation, and Bhabha Atomic Research Centre (BARC). I am currently also serving as the Vice President of the UT Chapter of SIAM (Society for Industrial and Applied Mathematics).

Education

The University of Texas at Austin

Austin, TX

Ph.D. in Computational Engineering and Sciences - CGPA: 4.0/4.0

August 2019 - May 2024

The University of Texas at Austin

Austin, TX

MS IN COMPUTATIONAL ENGINEERING AND SCIENCES - CGPA: 4.0/4.0

August 2019 - May 2021

Indian Institute of Technology Bombay (IIT-Bombay)

Mumbai, India

B.Tech in Mechanical Engineering - CGPA: 9.32/10.0, Department Rank - 4/150

July 2015 - May 2019

• Graduated with a Minor degree in Computer Science and Honors in Mechanical Engineering

Experience

GRADUATE RESEARCH ASSISTANTSHIP

Paleochronometry as a control problem for recovering Holocene climate variations over the Greenland Ice Sheet

Austin, TX

Advisor - Patrick Heimbach, Research Group - CRIOS

September 2020 - Present

- Integrated the open source Automatic Differentiation tool Tapenade with the SICOPOLIS ice sheet model source code in order to generate the adjoint and tangent linear codes. The adjoint calculation of the gradient is exponentially faster than the finite differences calculation.
- Built fully automated CI pipelines on TravisCI for containerized adjoint validation using Docker and pytest
- Successfully inverted for the source term of the mass equation for a basic mountain glacier model, leveraging the adjoint method to calculate the gradient along with second order quasi-Newton methods such as BFGS and L-BFGS for optimization
- · Collaborations with Argonne National Laboratory, Hokkaido University, and French Institute for Research in Computer Science and Automation

Deep Learning Emulator for the Dynamics of Sea Ice

Austin, TX

Advisor - Patrick Heimbach, Research Group - CRIOS

August 2021 - Present

- Leveraging Deep Learning to reduce the computational cost of simulating sea ice in the general ocean circulation model, MITgcm
- Collaborations with MIT, Scripps Institute of Oceanography (in UC San Diego)

PROJECTS IN HPC, DATA SCIENCE AND MACHINE LEARNING

Mudrock Prediction from Wireline Logs Using Machine Learning

Austin, TX

Advisor - Sergey Fomel, Oden Institute, UT Austin

January 2021 - May 2021

• Developed a program to automatically pick mudrocks from wireline logs using Machine Learning algorithms on a real dataset. XGBoost and CNN found to be the best algorithms, with about 87% test accuracy. First (known) attempt to utilize this for pore pressure prediction, an important geological application. The work can be extended to map lithology across basins.

Physics Informed Neural Networks for Mountain Glaciers

Austin, TX

Advisor - Rachel Ward, Oden Institute, UT Austin

January 2021 - May 2021

• Leveraged PyTorch, and GPUs/TPUs on Google Colab in order to train a Deep Neural Network that emulates the solution of highly non-linear and diffusive glacier model. Another aspect of the project involved inferring the parameters of a non-linear, diffusive PDE using a Neural Network given that the behavior of the PDE is known at certain points in spacetime. The diffusion makes the problem highly ill-posed.

Laplacian 2D Finite Difference (FD) solver application

Austin, TX

Advisor - Karl Schulz, Dept. of Women's Health, Oden Institute, UT Austin

August 2020 - December 2020

• Features: Solver (gauss, jacobi, PETSc), tests (bats, Travis CI, Docker), 98% code coverage (lcov), 0% memory errors (Valgrind), build (Autotools), HPC env (SLURM), Storage (HDF5), parser and logger (GRVY), code verification (MASA), version control (github), OOP (C++)

Bayesian Inference of Uncertain Model Parameters using Real Data

Austin, TX

ADVISOR - ROBERT MOSER, ODEN INSTITUTE, UT AUSTIN

January 2020 - May 2020

Applications included the Energy Balance Model model for climate change calibrated to surface temperature data, and stokes drag calibrated
with laboratory measurement data collected at UIUC. Applied Markov Chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) methods using Python in order to efficiently
sample high-dimensional parameter spaces and derive posterior distributions, thus testing the theoretical frameworks against real data.

Analysis of Parallel Computing Techniques on Generalized-lpha method

Mumbai, India

ADVISOR - SHIVASUBRAMANIAN GOPALAKRISHNAN, DEPARTMENT OF MECHANICAL ENGINEERING, IIT BOMBAY

January 2018 - May 2018

Performed a comparative analysis of numerical simulations of the popular Generalized-α method (both explicit and implicit) which is used in
computational structure dynamics to model fluid structure interactions as spring mass systems using parallel computing tools like OpenMP,
 CUDA and MPI. Achieved upto 7x speedup using MPI and upto 5x speedup using Nvidia CUDA.

PROJECTS IN COMPUTATIONAL FLUID DYNAMICS AND COMPUTATIONAL SOLID MECHANICS

B.Tech Thesis - CFD simulations for Boiling in Nuclear Rod Bundles using OpenFOAM

Mumbai, India

ADVISOR - JANANI SRREE MURALIDHARAN, DEPARTMENT OF MECHANICAL ENGINEERING, IIT BOMBAY

July 2018 - May 2019

Verified trends of Eulerian solvers against experimental results for flows over nuclear rod bundles. Applied OpenFOAM, an open-source code
 (C++) to the area of subcooled boiling. Trained Machine Learning models using existing data on 8 mm tubes to predict values of fluid quality for
 new rod bundle cases after applying suitable conversion factors, achieving 76% accuracy.

Collaborations with Bhabha Atomic Research Centre (BARC), Mumbai, India

1D Linearized Shallow Water Equations using Finite Element Methods

Mumbai, India

ADVISOR - SHIVASUBRAMANIAN GOPALAKRISHNAN, DEPARTMENT OF MECHANICAL ENGINEERING, IIT BOMBAY

July 2018 - November 2018

Solved the 1D hyperbolic equations for shallow water systems using continuous and discontinuous Galerkin methods and compared results for
different sets of nodes such as uniformly spaced, Chebyshev, etc. Conducted spectral analysis of linear system in order to verify convergence.

2D Navier-Stokes Solver for Incompressible Flows using Finite Volume Methods

Mumbai, India

ADVISOR - ATUL SHARMA, DEPARTMENT OF MECHANICAL ENGINEERING, IIT BOMBAY

July 2017 - November 2017

• Developed Finite Volumes based 2D Navier Stokes solver using Semi-Implicit Method for Pressure Linked Equations for lid driven cavity case

PROJECTS IN MANUFACTURING, MICROPROCESSORS, AND CONTROL

Bionic Handling Assistant Mumbai, India

Advisor - Parag Tandaiya, Department of Mechanical Engineering, IIT Bombay

July 2018 - November 2018

• Designed a simple prototype arm based on the trunk of an elephant. Modeled the kinematic analysis of the system in spherical co-ordinates. Designed and implemented an algorithm to control the motion of the trunk using multiple arduinos simultaneously.

PID Position Control Mumbai, India

Advisor - Shashikanth Suryanarayanan, Department of Mechanical Engineering, IIT Bombay

January 2018 - May 2018

Applied PID based accurate and responsive correction to a position control function for a DC Motor attached to a gear. Fine-tuned PID control
coefficients and validated trends against Simulink models.

Dependence of Friction Coefficient on Texture

Mumbai, India

Advisor - Ramesh Singh, Department of Mechanical Engineering, IIT Bombay

July 2018 - May 2019

• Developed CNC codes to create textures on polished stainless steel surface using SPI Laser 100 at different intensities and measured coefficient of friction using self-made apparatus. Analyzed trends for Friction Coefficient vs Energy per unit length for different combinations of textures.

INTERNSHIPS

ITC Limited, India's Largest FMCG Conglomerate

Kolkata, India

ADVISOR - AURKO CHATTERJEE, MANUFACTURING MANAGER (CURRENTLY GLOBAL SUPPLY MANAGER AT APPLE)

May 2018 - July 2018

- Interned in the packaging section of ITC's only fully owned flour plant near Kolkata, West Bengal, India
- Manpower Reduction in Primary Packing Machines Identified priority target areas and used 5-Why analysis to determine root causes, Reduced operator involvement by 27% through increase in no-touch times by setting up feedback systems to control dosing of flour into pouches.
- Downtime Reduction of Secondary Packing Machines Machines worth \$275,000 were dysfunctional due to high downtimes. Achieved 40% reduction in downtime frequency via PDCA-cycle based improvements. Prepared standard inventory lists to quicken response to downtimes.
- Results: Manpower reduction by 50% in the packaging section, 60% machines running with no major downtime

Publications & International Conferences

Shreyas Gaikwad, Sri Hari Krishna Narayanan, Laurent Hascoet, Ralf Greve, Patrick Heimbach

"SICOPOLIS-AD v2: An open-source tangent-linear and adjoint modeling framework for ice-sheet simulation enabled by the AD tool Tapenade", 24th EuroAD Workshop, 2021

Virtual



Languages Python (scikit-learn, Keras, PyTorch, FENICS, numpy, autograd, Pandas), C++ (GRVY, MASA, HDF5, PETSc), FORTRAN-90

Softwares MATLAB, Scilab, Solidworks, ANSYS, ADAM, OpenFOAM, Simulink, MTpX, Tapenade, MITgcm, SICOPOLIS

HPC OpenMP, MPI, CUDA, SLURM

Other Tools Github, Docker, Shell scripting, Travis-CI, Autotools, Valgrind, HTML, CSS, Jekyll, Icov

Relevant Graduate level Coursework

Data Science Machine Learning applications in Geophysics, Foundational Techniques in Machine Learning, Engineering Data Mining

HPC Design and Analysis of Algorithms, Tools and Techniques in Computational Science, Numerical Methods for Differential

Equations, Numerical Linear Algebra, High Performance Scientific Computing, Operating Systems

Inverse problems Uncertainty Quantification in Computational Models, Computational & Variational Methods for Inverse Problems (observer)

Mathematics Functional Analysis, Partial Differential Equations, Analytical Methods

Fluid Dynamics Phys. Oceanography, Mathematical Modeling in Science and Engineering, Computational Fluid Dynamics, Galerkin Methods

Honors & Awards_

FELLOWSHIPS & SCHOLARSHIPS

2019	Peter O'Donnell Fellow , Awarded Fellowship worth \$24,000 by the Oden Institute.	Austin, IX
2015	KVPY Fellow, Conferred by Govt. of India for demonstrating aptitude for research, Rank - 27/50,000	Mumbai, India
2015	INSPIRE Scholar , Awarded scholarship for top 1 percentile standing in class XII examinations	Nashik, India
2012	Bhaskar Genius Scholar, Top 20 rank in India among 50,000 students	Nashik, India
2011	MCSE PSS Scholar, Maharashtra State Council of Examination, secured greater than 99.9995 percentile	Nashik, India

OTHERS

2020	Ph.D. Preliminary Exam , Passed exams in applied maths, scientific computing, and maths modeling	Austin, TX
2019	Honors in Mechanical Engineering, Awarded for completing B.Tech thesis, additional graduate coursework	Mumbai, India
2018	AP Grade , Awarded in Computer Graphics, very sparingly awarded for demonstrating exceptional insight	Mumbai, India
2017	AP Grade, Awarded in Heat Transfer, very sparingly awarded for demonstrating exceptional insight	Mumbai, India
2015	INChO qualification, Indian National Chemistry Olympiad, ranked top 1% among 30,000 students	Mumbai, India
2015	IIT Bombay Undergraduate Admission, widely regarded as the best engineering institution in India	Mumbai, India
2015	JEE Advanced qualification , Stage II entrance exam for the IITs, Ranked 509 out of 150,000 candidates	Mumbai, India
2015	JEE Main qualification, Stage I entrance exam for the IITs, Ranked 983 out of 1.5 million candidates	Mumbai, India
2015	BITSAT qualification, Entrance exam for the BITs, estimated rank top 200 among 300,000 students	Nashik, India

Mentorship, Leadership & Volunteer Experience _____

2021	Mentor , SIAM-UT Applied Math Mentorship Program	Austin, TX
2021	Vice President, University of Texas Chapter of SIAM	Austin, TX
2018	Mentor, Department Academic Mentorship Program, IIT Bombay	Mumbai, India
2018	Mentor, Academic Rehabilitation Program, IIT Bombay	Mumbai, India
2016	Volunteer , CURED, a pan-India initiative for diabetes (178 camps, 65,000 screenings in a day)	Mumbai, India
2015	Volunteer , Educational Outreach, National Service Scheme	Mumbai, India

Extracurriculars

Chess, Rated 1700 in the Rapid format and 1450 in the Bullet format on Lichess

Cricket, I follow cricket ardently and play as a bowling all-rounder

Reading, a personal collection of 100+ books across various genres such as fiction, history, political science